so let's look at the aat equation when
we have a cache hierarchy the aat is
still equal to L1 hit time plus the L1
Miss rate times the L1 Miss penalty but
it used to stop here and the L1 Miss
penalty would simply be the memory
access time but now we have that the L1
Miss penalty is the L2 hit time plus the
L2 Miss rate times the L2 Miss penalty
and the L2 Miss penalty is the L3 hit
time plus the level three Miss rate
times the level three Miss penalty and
so on until at some point we have a cash
whose Miss
penalty is equal to the main memory
latencies because there is no more
caches beneath it this cash whose misses
go directly to memory is called the last
level cach or
LLC so it used to be that the L1 cash
was the only cash so L1 cach was the LLC
then level two caches were introduced so
level two Miss penalty was the main
memory latency because level two went
directly to memory and that was the last
level cach and then level three caches
were introduced so they became the LLC
and so on